Diarmuid McDonnell

https://diarmuidm.github.io

Research Fellow, Third Sector Research Centre, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, B15 2TN, U.K. Research Fellow, AQMEN, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh, EH8 9LD, U.K.

RESEARCH AND TEACHING INTERESTS

I am a social scientist with experience in academia, the public and voluntary sectors, and consultancy work. My research explores the determinants of nonprofit misconduct, accountability and vulnerability, using linked administrative data derived from charity regulators internationally. I am currently researching post-war organisational change in the UK voluntary sector. I have methodological interests in the use of administrative data for social science research, data science and policy evaluation methods. My recent role involved scoping, organising and delivering knowledge exchange and networking events for businesses and academics interested in learning and applying data science approaches.

EDUCATION

2013 - 2017	PhD in Sociology & Social Policy, University of Stirling
2012 - 2013	MSc in Applied Social Research (Distinction), University of Stirling
2006 – 2010	BBus in Information Systems (1st class hons), Cork Institute of Technology

RESEARCH GRANTS

"Mission Accomplished? A Cross-national Examination of Charity Dissolution." *British Academy*, 2018-2019, £9,879.65 – Principal Investigator.

PUBLICATIONS

Peer-reviewed Journal Articles (Published)

- **McDonnell, D.**, & Rutherford, A. C. (2018) 'Promoting Charity Accountability: Understanding Disclosure of Serious Incidents' *Accounting Forum*, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.accfor.2018.05.003.
- **McDonnell, D.**, & Rutherford, A. C. (2018) 'The Determinants of Charity Misconduct' *Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly*, 47(1), 107-125.
- **McDonnell, D.** (2017) 'Improving Charity Accountability: Lessons From the Scottish Experience' *Nonprofit* and Voluntary Sector Quarterly, 46(4), 725-746.
- **McDonnell, D.** (2011). Co-operative Study and E-Learning: Lessons from Nova Scotia. *Journal of Co-operative Studies*, 44(3), 97-103.

Peer-reviewed Journal Articles (In submission)

Bhati, A., & **McDonnell, D.** 'Success in an Online Giving Day: The Role of Social Media in Fundraising' *Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly.*

Peer-reviewed Journal Articles (In preparation)

Rutherford, A. C., **McDonnell, D.**, & Hogg, E. 'Incentivising Regulatory Participation: Examining the Effectiveness of the Fundraising Levy'.

Peer-reviewed Book Chapters

- Edwards, R., **McDonnell, D.,** Simpson, I. & Wilson, A. (2017). Educational backgrounds, project design and inquiry learning in citizen science. In C. Herodotou, M. Sharples, E. Scanlon (Eds.). *Citizen Inquiry: A fusion of citizen science and inquiry learning*. London: Taylor & Francis.
- **McDonnell, D.,** & Macknight, E. (2015). Policy, principles, and practice: co-operative studies in higher education. In T. Woodin (Ed.). *Co-operation, Learning and Co-operative Values: Contemporary Issues in Education* (pp. 142-160). London: Taylor & Francis.

Books

- **McDonnell, D.,** Macknight, E., & Donnelly, H. (2012). *Democratic Enterprise: Ethical business for the 21st century*. Glasgow: Co-operative Education Trust Scotland.
- **McDonnell, D.,** & Macknight, E. (Eds.). (2012). *The Co-operative Model in Practice: International perspectives*. Glasgow: Co-operative Education Trust Scotland.

Selected Conference Papers, Reports, and Research Briefings

McDonnell, D., Punch, S., & Small, C. (2017). *Individual Wellbeing and Bridge: An Empirical Analysis*. English Bridge Education & Development (EBED).

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Year(s)	Role(s)	Module	Organisation
2017	Lecturer	Statistical Literacy (TPG, RPG, Staff)	Univ of Edinburgh
2017	Lecturer	Handling Data Management using SPSS (TPG, RPG, Staff)	Univ of Edinburgh
2013, 2015, 2017	Teaching assistant, Guest lecturer	Quantitative Data Analysis (TPG)	Univ of Stirling
2014 – 2016	Teaching assistant, Guest lecturer	Research Process II (UG)	Univ of Stirling
2015, 2016	Teaching assistant	Contemporary Social Issues in Practice (UG)	Univ of Stirling
2014	Lecturer	Responsible and Participative Management (TPG)	Univ of Stirling

2014	Teaching assistant	Research Process I (UG)	Univ of Stirling
2012 – 2013	Guest lecturer	Various business modules (UG, TPG)	Univ of the West
			of Scotland

RECENT AWARDS AND HONORS

Campbell Adamson Award for Best Paper, Voluntary Sector Studies Network Conference, 2018.

Campbell Adamson Award for Best Paper, Voluntary Sector Studies Network Conference, 2017.

Penn Doctoral Fellow (\$3000). Centre for Social Impact Strategy, University of Pennsylvania, 2016.

CAREER

2017 - 2018	Research Fellow, AQMEN, University of Edinburgh
2017	Research Data Service Assistant, EDINA, University of Edinburgh
2016 - 2017	Research Assistant, Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Stirling
2016 - 2017	Research Assistant, Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Stirling
2015 – 2016	Research Assistant, Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Stirling
2015	ESRC Research Student Placement, Scottish Government
2013 - 2014	Research Assistant, Faculty of Social Sciences, University of Stirling
2012 - 2013	Research Consultant, Self-employed
2010 - 2012	KTP Associate, University of Aberdeen and Co-operative Education Trust Scotland

GENERAL CONTRIBUTIONS TO ACADEMIC LIFE

Referee

Nonprofit and Voluntary Sector Quarterly

Faculty

2015 –	Active member of the Scottish Network for Third Sector Data
2014 – 2017	Active member of the Social Surveys and Social Statistics research group
2016	Helper at the British Society of Gerontology Conference 2016
2015/2016	PhD Representative, Faculty of Social Sciences

Professional Contribution Outside the University

2016	Presentation to board and staff of Scottish Charity Regulator on risk in the charity sector.
2016	Organised two ESRC Big Data Phase 3 networking events for third sector researchers.

Helped organise ESRC Festival of Social Science event "Community Resilience and Public Service Reform", attended by 40 individuals from government, local authorities, third sector organisations and academia.

Academically related Experience in the Community

2013 Board Member of UK Society for Co-operative Studies (a UK charity)